And
and do the pledge of allegiance.
Pledge allegiance to
the flag
The United States Of America.
>> To the Republic. For
which it stands.
One nation. Under
God.
Indivisible.
With liberty and justice for all. Okay.
>> All right, public speak.
Do we have anyone here for public speak?
Yes, I had a question if I might.
Certainly.
>> In
the June referendum,
we had these advisory questions.
And one of the questions
was concerned with
splitting the Andover elementary school budget in the town budget to be voted on
each independently.
And I was wondering if based on the results of that
question.
We should expect that to happen next time around.
>> I do not know the answer that question because that would be for the selectman would have to weigh in. And is that a charter change, Eric, I don't know, that does require a charter change.
>> Are selectmen asked that question because they were they're anticipating
another charter advisory commission to be seated sometime soon.
And they wanted that information to give them some direction.
Okay,
sounds good.
That's
>> all I had. Okay, thanks Jeff.
Nobody else public speak?
I don't see anybody.
All right, let's move. Do we have any additions or deletions that we want to add to the
agenda?
Does
anybody have anything? I have nothing.
I
apologize
>> guys, I was online at work until about an hour ago and then I needed to get dinner. But do we have anything on there for
tip
liaison?
For CIP?
Yeah.
>> But we have like 10 liaison reports. Yeah, that will address it then. That works. That's fine. That works? Okay.
All right. Thanks, Rob.
Go
ahead.
Ahead, Joanne.
Am I allowed to comment on the public speak
issue?
>> If you have a question. Yeah, I mean, I can't say one thing. I just think it would totally complicate our town even worse.
I think that somehow we all have to I understand
the theory
but I'm hoping that last year's situation
and things going forward
maybe preparing ahead of time
just might
do better and try to come together as a town to,
you know, I just feel like it's gonna be okay, got a 1% over here, we got a 4%, I don't know. It might complicate it, but it's for another, we've got a long time.
Thank you.
Eric.
>> Diane, can I suggest that you put under new business
affordable housing plan?
Okay,
that'd be eight H.
Yep.
Affordable.
Yeah.
Okay. Can I have a motion for that?
>> I'll
move to add NMH8H
affordable housing plan to the agenda.
Second.
Do I have a second?
Court seconds.
Any discussion?
Nope. All
in favor?
Aye.
Okay.
>> Unanimous. Okay.
Added.
All right. Anything else guys you want to add or delete?
We're good.
I'm good.
Okay.
Town administrators report.
Okay, can I share my screen?
Certainly.
Amanda, I need the power.
Okay.
>> Hopefully,
we're all looking at a shared screen
which says administrators report,
except it should say Board of Finance, not Board of Selectmen sorry.
Okay, so
things that are relevant to the Board of Finance. The first is the assessor's
office is on track to finalize the rebel
in October,
which will
probably fairly dramatically affect the grand list
doesn't
increase the amount of money we get it just means the overall grand list
will be higher.
So the other thing I wanted to make you guys aware of is that
the
Matea,
who was the person who had taken the combined position,
Well, was made to take the combined position
of the
assistant town clerk and the building admin has resigned
and taken another municipal job with Coventry.
So, the Board of Selectmen at their last meeting,
made a decision to split those positions back again, because of all the problems we had had with that
office.
So, we're advertising for them both separately.
And we will go from there.
>> Permit link is live question before you move on for that. So that has a financial impact to the budget because we have
a position that we didn't budget for correct.
>> That's correct. And
well, it's got two implications.
The first is
Mateo was taking a partial payment in lieu of health care.
And
since these are both union positions,
it is unlikely that we're not going to end up with,
a
significant change in the amount of benefits
associated
with these positions.
So
that's where that's where it becomes a Board of Finance
issue.
>> You know, not Eric are we back to the same hours previous to combining it for each position.
>> The
board is trying to run the,
the
building department right at twenty hours.
So,
you know, which is fourteen hours less than it was previously.
>> And then set hours so that the town people will know right I mean maybe you had that with the combined position to.
>> Mean, did, but it's,
it's been ugly.
Frankly, I would not be at all surprised if Bolton
refuses to sign another contract to provide building official services,
because they're obviously really unhappy with us.
>> Why
is it is it only working in an office is it the amount of work is so huge that one person just can't do it in those amount of hours.
>> There's a fair amount of work to that office.
The other real problem is that
when you have
a land building and land combined building and land use office,
where
everyone
is part time,
the building official part time zoning officials part time wetlands part time fire marshal is a few hours a week, When all those people are barely there,
you know, the admin
provides the gatekeeper that's
always there to answer questions.
And now when you say roughly half the time the building is open,
there's nobody there to answer questions.
Two things happen. One people get frustrated, and they call the Bolton Land Use Office directly,
because they know our building official,
you know, is in the end, their
admin
is quite unhappy to spend lots of time dealing with Andover's problems,
which makes everybody in Bolton unhappy.
Or they call the building official
for questions that really should be addressed by the admin, and the building official shouldn't directly be engaged. And when you only
are contracting for five hours a week of building official services,
that becomes kind of problematic in and of itself.
>> As a good administrative assistant in a department,
I would have a folder
with listed questions for those five hours that you can,
you know you got a doc I'm not saying it's a perfect world I totally hear what you're saying
I have to deal in my own capacity with people that I might see an hour a week I have that folder I've got it ready But I know what you're saying, that the people want the questions.
That's
if Matteo or the person was working twenty hours and had all those things lined up,
then you go week to week, or maybe the building official or whoever
has how many hours dedicated to Andover from Boland? Five.
Know that's not a heck of a lot of time to do. I love real estate, so it's not a lot of time to do permits and checking and,
you know, what so I imagine a lot of the work is doing that stuff, site work, too.
Yeah, I would just hope that I get that it's not easy,
but maybe
a little organization and having the questions all ready for it so that at least week to week,
the most time someone would have to wait for an answer is
a week. I don't know if that's reasonable or is that crazy too
>> in the building world. Well, I mean, there's so many variations
on questions
that I
think it's unreasonable
to expect
somebody else to cover that position and be able to understand,
know,
of the questions are and frankly,
you know, it's pretty obvious that whoever takes that position,
it's going to take them a long time
>> to get up to speed because there's a there's an enormous amount to know. Yeah. And if you if if you don't like it, like someone like me I'm just saying
I get that she can't answer or you know the person can't answer it just have those questions ready for when the
skilled person comes in
you know you could just go through them get the answers
get back to the person
I'm not saying it's that's how I organize my time I have like a staff of 150 that come at me and let me tell you teachers with COVID
and extra pay for this or this you just have to really
get your questions ready get the official that's going to answer them and then get back to the people all week.
So that's my world right now with COVID but
thank you. I don't want to
stall us.
>> Yeah, then how many hours will the assistant town clerk be
probably twenty six again.
>> And didn't you already bargain a position in the union to combine it so now it has to be split apart again or no? Well,
>> one, we never
originally,
you know, one the union never agreed to it. So, we never did formalize that.
We formalize what a combined position would make in terms of hourly wage,
but they have never agreed to
combine that.
We just did it because frankly they weren't, you know, playing ball with us period.
So,
you know, we're kind of back to where we were other than we're advertising this as a twenty hour a week position instead of a thirty
a thirty four hour a week position.
Eric?
>> Yep. Have you, run all this past or through the board of selectmen? Because I think that's an issue that they need to,
to deal with.
>> So I gave the Board of Selectmen a series of options,
and Sherry gave them the cost basis for what those options would be and what the cost would be for the town. And what what came out of that? Exactly
what I told you. Their decision was to have me split the position,
go back to a standalone position for the town clerk and a separate one for the building department.
Great.
>> And benefits for that, is there I forget when you earn benefits,
you know, with the whole
the retirement and all that. Is it 25 now? Did you up that? Nope. Those positions both will have benefits.
So on top of the salary, it'll be the what's the name? I'm sorry, I've had a long day. What's the name of the retirement program the town has again? I talked to it last week. I just can't think of it. The town is
in Murph.
>> Gotcha.
So
the 14 or 15%
that the town on each of those
on top. Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
>> And, you know,
mean, one of the issues we've had is as we've cut all this stuff,
you know, nobody stays anymore.
Yeah.
You know, we're on our third,
you know,
or second admin,
both admins have left within a year's timeframe.
After the one before that,
who had a little better package stayed for twenty something years, and is now back working as for the town temporarily filling in.
You know, we haven't been able to keep assistant town clerks any either,
>> because frankly, everybody else pays them a lot better. So they work for us for a short period of time, gain a little experience and both. And that's exactly what Matea did. Yeah, it's life life situations too. You're going to get a lot of, you know, I cut my hours in half when I was a young mom and had three kids at home. That was my priority it depends
it could be
great for someone but I get you you're not going to get people that are going to join on and stay forever it's just people's life circumstances that's all yep understood
>> all right thank you Okay, we are doing tree work.
Right now we're doing quite a bit of tree work over
on the northern half of the town.
We were fortunate that we
were able to make a deal with Eversource with the utility company.
And they basically agreed to allow us to cut on both sides of the road.
And they're paying for the cost of all the tree trimming and removal.
So that's allowed us to stretch our dollars a lot more.
That's been kind of a long running thing I've been trying to get.
You know, and it seems like we finally got to the right people at Eversource,
who are willing to consider some things like this.
So that's been going fairly fairly well.
As you know, we put aside
money in the tree work permanent fund.
This particular
iteration of tree work, we're going to expend somewhere between 35 and $40,000
And the utility company will put in that or maybe even a little bit more than that.
So that's been going fairly well.
>> We only put 50,000 in there for this fiscal year. Correct.
>> Correct. Well, we have to leave some for emergency stuff. Right. Right.
So,
there's no real report on snow plowing at this point but we did have an issue
with our contract
for salt.
So
there's
the
Connecticut is going to have a real problem with salt this year, because one of the main distribution points was in New London where they were able to barge the salt in.
And
New London has closed that facility
and turned it over to an offshore wind conglomerate.
So salt is either coming in from
now New Haven or South Of New Haven,
or somewhere in Rhode Island.
So there's a lot less supply available.
And one company has basically
bought out all the distribution
kind of in the Northeast.
We did sign a contract very early
with
in that contract specified that if the croc bid
came in lower than what we had locked in at,
we would be able to they would honor the croc bid.
Unfortunately,
they were one of the companies that were bought out the company that bought them out.
Apparently bought their
salt stockpile
and didn't really buy anything else from them. So they have told us they will not honor it.
We have
been able to get back in on the state bid
for salt.
So it looks like we're going to be okay,
probably.
But this is going to be a real issue going forward
in years.
The good news is we have a really good stockpile of salt.
So you know, we may be able to get away with only purchasing say 300 tons this year.
You know, if we start having supply issues,
not ideal, but you know, that is life.
So
as you all know, we sent out and got back the RFPs for the community center.
The,
the
committee approved hiring the BSC group for the excavation site work
for twenty three thousand dollars
and Moser pile on Nelson architects for the architectural for part $6,000
So I sent the details
to the town's attorney and asked him to write up a contract.
He got a contract back to me
this morning for the excavation
site work.
And he basically said the architectural bid
was a low enough dollar amount, he said just sign the bid document they gave you and you'll be fine. So presuming the Board of Finance has no objection.
My plan was to sign that tomorrow and get both of those off
and running.
>> So let me ask that question.
Because you sent me that lovely purchasing
policy.
If it's,
>> so we don't need a formal contract if it's between 5 and 15,000.
That's how I'm reading that.
Right.
That is correct.
Okay.
Perfect.
>> Eric, before we go any further on the salt budget thing.
Yep.
My question would be, alright, so we signed a contract with somebody for kind of a price protection
contract.
They get bought out and now we'll honor the contract.
What sort of dollar amount
are we talking about here? Because I'm just thinking whether there's any purpose here in trying to
to enforce something?
It's a small amount of money, it's not worth pursuing them.
>> Know, who knows where salt prices are going to
end up?
At this point, it seems like we're
going to be they will accept us under the state bid contract.
So we're going to be paying roughly what we paid.
We would have paid had we had a standalone contract,
maybe a tiny little bit more, but not enough to worry about.
Okay, you know what the company the original
agreement was to lock us in at about 70,
I think $75
a ton.
And the company
that bought them, they didn't actually buy them out. According to them, All they did, the only thing they agreed to do was buy their salt stockpile.
But since
they can essentially prevent the other company
from importing salt, because they now no longer have a way to do it, because they control all the importation.
They essentially took over their client or they took over their stuff because the other company has no way to get product.
>> Yeah, I don't want to belabor this,
it doesn't necessarily relieve
the seller
of its contract.
You know, if it's a straight asset purchase and they only purchase the stockpiles, I get that. But then the the company that made the agreement with us still exists,
still has assets or whatever.
That doesn't necessarily just mean they get to walk away and stiff us.
Now, if it's a small amount of money, it doesn't make any sense to to pursue them. I understand that. But I'm a little,
I don't want to just
hand wave this away
because typically
when you have like this is this apparently what you're telling me is that this isn't the corporate successorship issue
where they actually
completely bought out the company. The other company still exists, right? Still a going concern?
No.
They're
done.
Mean,
they have no product.
>> Yeah. Okay. So they sold.
Hang on. Yeah. Somehow they sold their assets, but not their liabilities.
Yeah. I'm not sure that flies, but okay.
That bothers me. Sorry. This is the insurance guy in me. I
don't love that. But if it's not a huge amount of money and it's not worth pursuing, fine.
I just
It doesn't strike me as the right answer, but okay. Well,
>> and Rob, you know this and you know, because contracts are contracts, but if the company was acquired,
then they would have to, you know,
most contracts aren't assignable, so they're not going to go, you know, so the thing is, we don't know what the legal status is of the company is.
>> Right. And whether they're actually dissolved or what have. Right. I
get what you're saying. That's what I'm bringing up.
Now I deal with corporate successorship issues in a very different context.
And this is exactly the sort of thing that we get stuck on a fair bit in my job.
Who actually has the rights and who actually has the responsibilities?
But
this is a massive rabbit hole and I don't want to go down any further. So let's move on. Yeah. I'm happy to give you the information if you wanna sue them.
Yeah.
>> I am not legal counsel. So let's just
don't listen to me.
I I I just bugged me and it struck me as the wrong answer. But hey, again, let's move on. Sure. Okay.
>> So I'm not going over everything on here. Just so that you know, in the interest of time.
So,
we
got our,
our
essentially full approval for the steep grant for that will cover the cost half the cost of reclaiming
a couple of roads.
We're not going to get to it this year because we're way too far behind on drainage work and we got to finish complete the drainage work on Shoddy Mill before we do it because we have to do both roads at once. But the good news is,
at least they finally fully approved
the,
the funding for this deep grant.
So we know the money is there when we get around to doing it.
The connectivity
grant,
we finally got the official notice to proceed from Department of Transportation
project authorization
list,
and they wrote us a check for $297,000
So we have the money.
I'm still bugging the, the construction company
as to when the actual start date is.
But it sounds like it's going to be fairly soon they're trying to wrap up other projects right now.
Before they started on it. So hopefully we'll get the significant portion of that completed
this fall.
>> Remind me, Eric,
what's included in that connectivity?
Is the what what's the work they're going to be doing.
Say
again, is it sidewalks.
>> It's part it's a it's a series of connected things. Okay. So, the idea
was,
we got the dot separately
to install a new
crosswalk
across
Long Hill Road at Route 6.
And then we're tying it in with sidewalks
running down to the bridge towards the ball field,
and then improving
the other side connecting to the rail trail, making a new
trail head there,
installing a kiosk,
New stairs at the library.
New handicapped accessible ramp and railing at the library
connection
to the
in connection to the
Andover Church there.
So it's basically
the goal is to make an easy pedestrian and cycling connection
now between,
you know, the North Side and the South side at Long Hill between the ball field and the rail trail and other town assets.
>> I would love them to have a flashing stop ahead
sign when you're coming up to Long Hill there because that corner is just
the light changes, you don't see it.
>> Well, we did at least get the DOT
to do a lot of cutting there. Yeah. So they did push the brush back a lot. And light is still screwed up there.
You know, which is not good because they,
the the new crossing
and the new traffic lights are
keyed on cameras,
not on underground
sensors,
you know, underground magnetic sensors,
which is kind of the way they're all going to.
But the company that's got that project
is a little over a year behind.
Mean, was supposed to be completed
last.
It was supposed to be done by October
1.
And they still haven't finished the bloody thing so.
So that's a little annoying.
But,
you know, that's the state's problem more than it is our problem, because that's not part of our grant that was another project,
we got the state to do for us. Okay.
So
as far as town wide monitoring.
As most of you know, we had to switch
from monitoring by our talent
dispatch center
to our own standalone
company,
not our own company, but a commercial company.
So we did that,
we made a decision who we went
transition took place by July 1. And then we've been going all around
and getting all the buildings inspected and then brought back up to code.
There were some a number of problems identified.
The worst ones were in public works, which we already knew. And then also the town hall had a bunch of things that were pretty bad.
Like all the heat sensors
in the furnace room and in the attic here
were never wired correctly. So they never worked.
They all failed the initial tests. They just didn't go off.
And then when they went back and traced it,
they determined the sensor itself was Okay, but they were incorrectly wired.
So the town hall is not that inexpensive a set of fix.
And I already cleared that work with the fire marshal
to make sure he was okay with what they were doing there.
And then public works,
that's going to be about 85 or $8,000
it's less than the Board of Selectmen and you as the Board of Finance agreed to
when we when you
signed off on the whole proposal back in July.
So
they were originally saying if they had to replace everything,
it was going to be in the 12,000 to $14,000
range.
And so what we decided on doing was just inspect everything first,
and then let's bring it up to code, and let's replace just what's physically failing or not code compliant.
So that's basically what we're doing.
Next thing up.
We talked a number of times with the Board of Finance about the affordable housing grant.
We did get an affordable housing grant from
the state
HUD,
or some other entity of the state.
And we did an RFP for that we got three bids back for it.
And the
planning and zoning commission accepted the bid from Bill Warner,
as the lowest cost acceptable bid.
And I think the reason,
Bill was able to provide this at a lower cost was because A, he wrote our last plan and conservation and development,
and B,
he
won the bid for
the last affordable housing grant
that we got
about ten years ago. So he was basically starting with a
significant fraction of the data.
So I'm informing you this. My intention is just to announce the bid acceptance
and
write a contract with Mr. Warner, unless
you all as a board have an issue with it, or want to discuss it in some form or another.
I don't have an issue. Anybody have any issue?
>> No issue. And it's been talked out, talked about for a number of meetings. So yeah, I'm gonna do that. Yep. Okay.
>> So I think I've already told you this or Sherry already told you this. But we did get our first tranche of the American Recovery Act funding
for $470,000
of which you've agreed to spend
around $1,200
by writing a check to the health district.
But other than that, so you have basically
$477,000
of that still in the
in the kitty.
The other thing I wanted to talk to you about that you're
going to see coming up is that
we had the the board had already had asked me to
instead of directly doing the electrical work that we needed in the town hall to send that to RFP.
As soon as I prepared the RFP that set off a little bit of an argument within the board of selectman
about scope of work.
Partly because there's a fairly significant
code violation
in our mechanical room.
And that when they did the addition for the community room,
they ran the fill lines for the new oil tank directly over the electrical panel, which is clearly a code violation.
I'm not saying our
because what we were going to add to the system
would have not been directly under it. We probably could have done it but the Board of Selectmen did not feel comfortable,
you know, continuing something that that was that bad a
code violation.
The problem is is that that led to mission creep. And
if we replace that, then really,
there's a couple other things we really ought to do at the same time. Because if we're redoing all the piping,
the only way we can do redo the piping is to go through an existing window
area that was already
turned into a vent. So we're going to have to block that off.
And there's going to be a number of other things. So it's, it's gone from a simple project
to
a complicated,
more complicated project that's going to result in us replacing our oil storage tank,
our fill pipes,
doing a little work on the H vac which we know we've needed to do.
You know, and some, you know, some masonry.
So the board has also asked me to
apply for low SIP funds to pay for that upgrades.
And we have plenty of money
available in our low SIP account. We should be able to pay for that strictly with the low SIP funds and not touch the building maintenance funds
to do that makes it a lot more complicated
project with a lot more moving parts.
But
and it's going to push the time we do it out a little bit. But
yeah,
that's that's kind of the plan at this point.
Do any of you have any questions
about what we're doing or why?
>> I listened to that meeting, so it was a lively meeting.
They usually are.
>> Also,
Eric, ran it through
capital improvements last Thursday.
And personally, I think the amount of the cost for the entire project is not
really crazy or out of the ordinary. And
as
I think we all stated,
know, the town needs to meet code with that upgrade.
You might as well complete the upgrade while we're doing it.
You have to see some hard facts and figures, think we'll be okay.
>> Yep, yep, that's what I'm working on providing.
Okay,
so that's
everything
I have other than I do have the
stuff.
And we can go into it. I'll unshare my screen and then share it again.
When we get to the discussion for
CIP, the excavator and the other stuff.
And that's it for me unless you have other questions for me.
>> Anybody have any other questions for Eric before we go over to Sherry?
No? Okay, Sherry, you're up.
>> Okay.
Good evening.
In your packet,
have
several reports.
I submitted to you
the town budget summary from last fiscal year 2021
and
the revenue summary
from last fiscal year as well
and the TAR spending
account
in detail. That's where we are at with all three of those reports.
I expect that the budget summary
report will reflect
two more adjustments.
We have two
things to pay before
September 30, and then that should be officially closed out at that time.
I'm also working on reconciling
the town with the Board of Ed,
and coming
up with a final total as far as the PO encumbrances that we still need to
do
and pay out.
So
I'm
working on that and there's some adjustments to that, but it's not gonna be
earth shattering and it should be fine.
And the other thing is the second set of reports,
well actually one set of reports,
is your new
report for
the software
system that we put into place.
I am working with the programmer.
There's a final column on that report that should be there
called percentage used,
and it's not there because
it places a whole
dollar
amount in there and not a percentage amount like I want them
to have.
So
they're working with the programmer on that.
And a couple of the reporting
format issues
I want changed,
and
hopefully I'll have them
rectified by the next
month.
And I can give you a full
report the way it looks like, but pretty much the way you see it now is what it's going to be like.
I think it's user friendly.
I added all the accounts that you requested,
departmental wise, for
the benefits.
We have those in place.
And
what I'm adding now is the revenue accounts.
And also, I'm setting up
other fund accounts.
>> Have a couple questions.
So let's go to the fiscal last fiscal year end report in there. So right now that report
was run I think in the middle of July, third week of July, and it shows that there's a $600,000
surplus. So there still are things that have to be paid
and everything on that. Yes.
>> And there's a total amount.
I'm
trying to get the encumbrances down for the border bed. We're receiving invoices right now. I want to process them
so that what I end up with is a total
purchase orders that are left to pay. In other words, we're waiting for more invoices to come in.
Things are back ordered.
There's certain things that are discontinued.
I'm trying to get a final number for that to book
as far as
the board of directors. Then
we'll have a final
figure.
>> Okay.
So
last fiscal year, when do you think we're going to have a
basically
put that to bed kind of done as an accurate final report?
>> Some I'm working on to have it finished by September 30, which is next week. Oh, next meeting. Oh, next meeting that you have
should be the final report.
>> Perfect.
Diane, can I ask her one question to pay Just back
your question?
So Sherry, that's unusual
with these invoices that are still outstanding.
When were those things ordered?
>> Were prior
to June 30.
They were ordered in May.
Yeah. A lot of the companies because of COVID
don't have a full operational
staff back in in
the building. So
there have been a lot of things that have been discontinued
or
back order.
Me a simple, very simple example.
We received a kidney table, what is called a kidney table the other day. Yeah, yeah.
And
four legs are missing.
No, no legs.
Okay.
So we just called the company to kind of rectify that. They're going to they apologize
because they're using a third party shipping company.
And
apparently they forgot them on the truck. So
I'm still trying to get that issue
rectified hopefully by the end of this week.
And then we can put that one to bed. But that's just a very small
example of what kind of things that we're dealing with. I
>> face this as well. So I just want to make sure were these things that were ordered in May,
things that were previously
budgeted
and not just
extra money left over to be spent because it was in the right category and then ordered
>> that late in the year. They were ordered in the right category.
>> Oh, no. I'm sure. That I just mean it was budgeted at the beginning of the year,
and
it wasn't we had money left in this account. Let's spend it. Absolutely.
>> It was budgeted earlier.
Okay. Wasn't a lot of spending going on because we were, you know, taking a look at all the numbers and making sure that we
were well within our budget.
So
these were items that were scheduled to be ordered in the spring,
And they were ordered
and
we started receiving all the invoices. Unfortunately,
>> it's a lot slower than I would like to see happen. So I under yeah, no, thank you so much. I just wanted to make sure it wasn't extra spending and it was already planned spending. No, it was already planned. Thank you.
You're welcome.
>> Now I have
a bunch of questions on the new reporting.
Okay, so I just want to make sure
>> I'm understanding that. So, you know, it's a preliminary reporting.
So I'm still working till the final draft.
>> So when I look at this,
I see that there's a date at the top corner, 09/03/2021.
It looks like that's the date it was run. Current
period is 09/01/2021
to 09/3021.
Mhmm. So why
doesn't this go back to July? Is my first question.
July 1.
>> Current period, you're reporting on the current period,
which is September
1.
We have closed the month. Sorry. To me we should. Right, but you have current, you if you look on the column, it says expenditure current
that gives all the current amounts for September.
And then your year to date expended is your cumulative.
So this report
has July,
August,
and September.
>> And it's
kind of calculating like,
yeah, we move along.
>> But what
you put in is your September because you're reporting on the month of September and the activity that happened in the
current column expanded.
But it it keeps
adding
total cumulative
for the months that you have. Next month, there'll be October.
You'll have you'll see expenditure
current
column
with all the October
activities.
>> Current should be the current month we're in. Yes. Absolutely.
Yep. And year to date will include everything since the beginning of It includes July, August, and September,
obviously.
So it's I a
>> see that the
employee benefit things accounts have been moved into
the department
areas
and there's an adopted budget amount, but there's no
expended year to date or expended current amount
for those.
>> Yeah, we just received our bills.
Anthem Blue Cross Blue Shield was late in getting the billing out and we just received
all the bills that we had processed. So by the next
>> We would have Social Security and Medicare in there.
Right? We did payroll.
>> Yeah.
We have to do
probably Marina needs to do some journal entries.
>> So I'm thinking this is just a look at that budgeted amount in there, there's no items.
>> Just remember, she has to
do the amounts
Social Security. Yeah.
Social Security benefits and Medicare.
And then I told her she she now has to
do an additional entry to break that out departmentalize.
So that's what she's working on. Okay. The
percentage that she needs to put in all the departments.
Well, that'll correct all that. Okay. Yes, it will. Okay. I know she's working on that because she wants it as accurate as it can be. Okay. So those amounts
will be
reclassified
into their respective department. Okay.
>> So now I'm on page two,
and I'm in the tax collector
items.
And we have
negative balance
for equipment maintenance.
So I'm kinda wanna know what the hell is going on with that. Tax collector
equipment maintenance.
>> So we budgeted 8,800.
We expended $14.04,
and we have a negative 5,600.
So there's an over expense here.
Mhmm.
>> I'll have to take a look at We don't we don't know. Okay. We So don't have I can't tell you right now. I don't have the information.
I certainly will take a look at that. Okay.
And let me know what that is. It may be that because
these accounts are so new and I gave chart of accounts to Marina that, you know, we're just trying to get a feel for where things belong.
And I might have to reclassify
that particular
expense.
But I let me take a look at it and I'll let you know. Okay. So let me see my other
>> my other questions on that. Good question.
So now I'm on page four,
and I'm looking at
let's see what is payroll
service.
And we budget a $6,500
Do we pay payroll service on an annual basis or is there a monthly amount that we pay for payroll service? There is a quarterly bill that we receive and we pay it. Okay. Because nothing's in there year to date yet. So I'm just No. They haven't. They have not billed us yet and it usually comes in a quarterly.
Okay. Bob's bill. So
>> then if you look at that line item,
we budgeted 6,500,
but our balance is including an extra dollar 13. So Yeah. It's a big amount, I don't know what That's one of those things I'm working on with the programmer.
>> Okay, I'm using the reports are not working
the way they should be working.
And
he's calling me tomorrow morning.
And we're going to make sure that that's correct.
>> Oh,
so then again, we come into that whole employee benefits thing and I see where the year to date's in here, but not all the budget amounts are in there because we put them at the department level. So that's gotta be cleaned up. Okay. I'm following this now.
Right. It's on page five.
Let's
see.
Oh,
page seven.
Snow removal budget. We have overtime in there for snow removal. It's the summer.
We expended year to date 05/1959.
I'm assuming that's in the separate post.
Okay.
>> Is that Sorry.
That does not look right to me.
No.
>> I don't know if we have
a tree
work
overtime
>> or not. That must be Right. But this was just in the snow removal account. We have we shouldn't have anything expended in there yet. Yep.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Okay,
hold on. And then I'll reclassify it.
>> Have another negative balance on page eight under the fire marshal for $60
I
don't know if it's actually because we didn't
put the budget amount in or because there's no budget amount there. Right. But I don't know if that's correct or not. Do you know what I mean? So I can't tell.
>> So there's that. It means there's nothing has been assigned
in the budget column. So
let me see if I can double check and see what that is.
>> And I can tell you what that is.
And
that may be our issue with budgeting.
Because
when we so we added a burning official.
But we didn't budget for him.
And the reason we didn't budget for them is what we do is we simply pay the burning official,
the exact amount the town collects
when we issue a burning permit.
In other words, he gets paid a fee every time.
So he has to go out and do the inspections,
but he gets paid only what the person just directly paid the town.
So I mean, technically, we probably should have had
an anticipated
revenue from the burning official,
and then a line item for the burning official, but we did.
>> So we should account for that revenue,
we should know how much we're collecting on burning.
>> Right. I mean, we do we issue him.
We
basically pay him whenever,
you know, he gives us checks from the people who are requesting burning permits.
>> But we need some better way so it doesn't look like an overexpenditure all the time to deal with that. No. Proper way. When I'm setting up the revenue, you'll have a revenue
>> side,
which will show
all
that has been collected
in that particular
>> Okay. So department.
Alright. So let's go on to page nine.
Top of page nine, there's another negative balance of $686.
I have no idea why.
I don't know if that's because we have the adopted budget is not correct or the extended date is wrong.
>> That's the dues and fees, so I'm not sure. Yeah. So that's got to be classified
>> as well.
On
that same page, recreation.
Programs, recreation, commission.
We have a budgeted amount of $5,800
and two expended items, dollars 4,509
thousand $800
>> And the balance has not even the right balance for those numbers. Correct. And that's what I I told you. I'm working with the programmer. There is a problem.
>> Okay. We're on this report with that. Alright.
So when we get down to the transfer station items,
these
encumbered PO columns items in here.
Is that accurate or that should not be there?
Come or PO?
>> Yeah, because in other words, we have a budgeted amount. We have a year to date.
>> And then if we have a purchase order And then we're adding those back in.
If we encumber
no. Actually, it's not working the way it should be. Okay. So it was working the way it should be.
This
minus should be deducting it from
the year to date total.
That means we have a purchase order
that we're starting to do purchase orders now on the town,
just like we do on the board of Ed. Right. So we're starting to cover things
and then pay off of them.
So
that
>> is one of my areas that I'm having him take a look at. Okay. So this is all messed up. Carrie, has that not been done in the past, the purchase order system
>> on the town? Not to my knowledge. I have not. I've only been here since March, but
I'm told that
it hasn't been. So I'm trying to get
a system going so that we're
doing Checks and balance, yeah. Yeah, exactly what
we do on the board of that side where we encumber money.
>> And then on page 10, under the building department, there's a wages line that we budgeted for, but there is no year to date
payments out of that.
Do we have paid no wages so far this year into the building? Page 10.
>> So
the wages for the building department, the first line,
that is the fee for the shared service
for the building official. And again, they we get billed quarterly.
So we have not expended anything for that yet. Okay. Okay. Thank you. That's helpful. Thank you. Okay.
>> Alright.
So
these reports need a lot of work.
Yeah.
>> I'm a I am absolutely working with the program. I can only do what
the the company is working
on and trying to get done
in a very short period of time because I am beating them up on both sides.
>> Good. Because I'm
just getting concerned because we have a very, very tight budget
this year again.
And we're
coming into an, we're
gonna go into a quarter. And we, as a board of finance,
we have no real accurate financial reporting yet that we can kind of look at and make our decisions. So I just want to make sure that that's a priority and that we get some good numbers. It's a definite priority,
>> but I wanted you to have something rather than nothing
because I want you to know that it is being set up and
the chart of accounts is all in place, and
we're working with the software as far as the
doing accounts payable.
We're getting purchasing
installed
in
a system that we can rely upon.
The problem is the reporting is not what it should be, and I will make sure that it is.
>> Thank you so much Sherry. Anybody else have any questions? Know I took up everybody's time. I had time to look at this today so you know I looked through it all. Okay, that's fine. I just wanted to comment that I think it's really
>> easy to read. So I like the setup
once it gets accurate
information that Diane I looked at it also.
Just accurate information. I know you're working on it, so that's great. It's new.
I like the setup of it, easy to read, having looked at these things before. So yeah, just keep going, and
thank you for presenting it so we could see what it looks like. Thank you.
>> On the flip side,
last
few months I've been working on reconciling
the
town bank statement.
I
can honestly say that it's
reconciled through 06/30/2021
for the first time
since I've been there.
So we will have
I will have you, Eric, sign the very last one in June
approval,
and I will be calling the auditor tomorrow
to have him come in and let him know that we've reconciled the
bank statement all the way up to June,
and we're ready for him to start working on the audit on both sides.
Yay.
Yeah. I think that's good news. I was excited.
Job well done, Sherry, you and your assistant.
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. We've been working hard.
It's not perfect, but
>> we're getting there. It's nice to have a process with the encumbrances,
the POs.
I mean, you've got to have that trail. I don't even know how auditors would work in there before if, you know.
And one quick question because you mentioned auditors, so I hope I can comment.
Last month,
he presented a nice
PowerPoint
presentation. Amanda
was going to track it down and share it with us
just so that we'd have it. So
if he presented and there
was no hard copy left over. So thank you. We could get a copy of that. All right.
You're welcome.
>> Okay. So
we're onto budget transfers.
I have none. Okay. So let me ask a question. Since our financial reporting
is a little in a state of flux and everything, how are we managing if there's any over expenditures
and where we need to get approvals
>> by the Board of Finance? Well, we just got started.
So
I have a feeling a lot of it where it is now is just needs to be reclassified to the right account.
So I don't believe we have any major over expenditures where we're gonna have to
get approval on them at this point.
Okay. I mean, we're up until September.
It's only three months.
You know, I think we'll we'll be fine. I'll take a look at all those accounts. I'll work with the programmer.
I'll see where we're at. If there needs to be something, I'll bring it forward next
time around, but I don't foresee that happening
right now.
Okay. Perfect.
Right.
>> Diane, can I ask her one? Go ahead. Go ahead. Just a quick thing to get the sorry, just because it's going to be so tight this year.
And
we made a promise that we were going to when I ran, I was questions all along and not just wait till the end.
So
with those items, Sherri, that were ordered in May for the school side,
were they necessary
to order
for the running of school last year?
I mean, know they were planned spending.
Yes, they were necessary.
>> Okay, to be used. So they're used up, whatever A lot of is
curriculum.
Speaking to the curriculum.
Yeah. Very important.
I
>> work in a school, so I do get that. Yeah. And that's why I'm telling you that. So you can understand where I'm coming from. Yeah. So
yes, it was absolutely necessary.
>> So because you said there's like 600,000
outstanding
that you'll be paying invoices to.
>> I didn't say 600,000.
Okay, I
said there was a sum of money
that has been encumbered.
It's nowhere near 600,000.
It's
probably at this point
under
75,000.
I'm trying
very hard to pay it all down so that I have a very small encumbrance
leftover,
which I have to book on the downside.
So it's not going to pull a lot from the bottom line is what I'm
telling Okay.
>> So and it was all necessary, of course, curriculum. Okay, thank you. Yes.
>> Okay.
We are under old business.
You kind of gave us a do you have anything else to say about your software transition or anything like that? Mean, said you're kind of working with them to get the report straightened out. No, that's
>> the only thing that I'm a little
upset about is the reporting capability.
But I think we'll be able to work
through
what the program is on that. And I'm sure it's something
that
the cells of certain expenditures are not
working the way they should.
So I hope to have that resolved very soon.
Other than that, they are very responsive to us.
They when we call them for help, they are there
helping us every step of the way. They've been more than
accommodating.
So I just want to let you know that that to me is a big comfort because
we're not left alone
and lurch without,
you know, some support and guidance that we need right now. Once we go through this for a year,
we'll we'll know
what's going on and how to do things and should
be all the bugs
should be worked out of it and we should be fine.
Other than that, I think it was a smooth transition.
I thought it was very easy to learn
the system. I've learned other systems, and
it's pretty user friendly.
So
I'm excited about it.
Good.
Okay. Item 7B audit status.
I'm
calling in tomorrow to get them in here.
>> I wanted to ask one question in here under audit.
I'm going back to the last audit that was just completed
and the corrective action items.
So
we had one significant
deficiency identified
on financial reporting
that was a repeat finding,
and it was
utilizing balance sheet accounts, recording revenue and expenditures, they wanted us to fix that. And we said we were going to fix it with the
deployment
of this new accounting system.
Is
that being done? I just want to get a status on that because the other two corrective action items have been completed and this one's outstanding. So I just want to make sure that we're going to see that fixed
and it's going to be happening.
>> That is part of the
other
part of it is me
setting up revenue accounts and expenditure
accounts
for those liability
accounts that were put on the books
and they shouldn't be there. Right. So I I met with him and I know exactly what accounts he's expecting us to
do.
And I will be doing that
momentarily.
>> I'll be working on that. Okay. So I'm going to keep this on the agenda so we just don't lose sight of it. So we know that because I don't want it falling into next year. Well, I have one of the things I have to do is write a corrective
>> action plan
and submit it to the auditor so he could submit it to the state.
And that will be all part of my written
presentation
to him
of how we're going to fix these things. And with that
being said, I will work on on that to complete
so that the audit for
will include those adjustments.
And that should go away.
That should be fine.
>> I have the only outstanding
corrective item is those accounts to be fixed. So so we already fixed the ACH controls. We already fixed the controls over payroll. Yeah. Yeah. That's the major one. The major one is what you said.
And
we'll have that fixed.
Okay.
>> Now
bear in mind, since we didn't adopt
this
software,
essentially until after the last fiscal year closed,
you know, I suspect we might see that audit finding again
on
the audit
that he's starting right now, because I know.
Not completed during the
>> repeats going to be a third time but I want to be able to say when he sees it the third time that we can say it's all fixed with the new system period and we can see it being done. Actually, would think that's the fourth time we've
gotten on the I don't want to see it going beyond this fiscal year. I want it to be fixed. Well,
>> to be honest with you, you had to hire me before.
>> I know. I mean, you have the past is the past. Got me in March, so it's been seven months.
Know,
>> I think I'm doing One of the issues we have as an organization
is no one ever tracked,
you know, deficiencies coming out of audit reports and corrective action items to see that they were done. So
I'm going to start doing that.
>> That's good because my reputation is not to have any deficiency
And then on it. And I never have. So
I'm gonna make sure that goes away.
That'll go away.
Yippee.
>> Sherry, you're cleaning up a lot of stuff for sure.
I watched it. Not I mean, we all know.
>> Yeah. Keep it going. It's going good. Yep. One day at a time is what I say. Absolutely.
>> We already kind of got an update on the community senior center building committee. Because they were kind of targeted. We went to, you know, we've got the contract going on that. So,
let's go on to new business.
Okay, Eric, ran multiuse turf field project.
So, is this the
age old question? Are we going to,
an organization,
a town
come out for or against it or.
>> Well, item is supposed to be. You are the board of finance,
right? And this will be a $70,000
per year ongoing expense.
If it gets passed.
So
it's certainly in your domain to comment on this for or against as a board if you so choose,
You may not choose to do that. You may choose to be silent.
But
if you decide
as a board you're forward or against it, you probably ought to state that publicly.
Since I think people would look for the Board of Finance to provide a little guidance on that.
>> The last question I have on this is it definitely
passed
their last meeting to go to referendum. It's officially going on the ballot
November 2, think is the date. Correct. There will be
a vote on this.
Yep.
Where I myself
personally sit on this, I just think it's a lot of money.
>> I would say that, you know, if you just think back to the budget cycle we just completed,
if we had come to the town with a $70,000
increase,
we couldn't get that passed.
We all know this. We had to zero out everything to get a budget passed.
So,
you know, my general take,
I'm not always a complete hardliner about these things, but I
would find it immensely frustrating
if
after that
we tacked on 70 k a year for how many years? What is it? You know five six years Eric remind me ten years ten years
after
that battle that we just had to tack on 70 a year like it was nothing
No, I personally
think
it's perfectly fair for this board to point out
that this is a bad idea,
especially in context with what we've been dealing with,
you know, in our Andover budgeting.
It's not okay,
in my opinion,
if we're shorting in comparison,
you know, our own school and our own town.
I mean, as Erica said repeatedly, we're right to the bone here on the town budget.
You know, I think it's a bad idea.
>> And we also said at the last meeting, it was kind sneaky that it kind of came to be right after
the tough budget season,
you know, to pull this out, have all these meetings,
you know, it just,
was
so what RAM does,
You know, they don't take into consideration
any timeline, anything that just happened in all of the towns.
You know, again, I know we talked about it a lot last meeting, and nothing's changed for me. It was really a sneaky time when we had that hard budget season to just propose this start having meetings
end of the summer so I'm definitely not in favor
>> We don't know where the board of selectmen
land on this yet. Right? They've I've been to all the meetings. They've just talked about it. No one's really come out and officially said
yay or nay. Mean
>> They brought up some counter proposals
of possibly doing, you know, digging up.
And again, I don't know the technical thing. You know I watch sports but
digging up the grass field and maybe doing another thing like that to a tune of maybe 800,000
you know so upper you know so they asked all the right questions but you're right I don't know where they
I don't know if they publicly,
I didn't get to the end of the tape on the meeting. I don't know if they publicly said yay or nay.
>> So
realistically,
you know, it's going to referendum. So end of story, you know, all the discussion is off the table now with this.
Our only recourse right now as a town is to
write a letter and say, you know, we don't support it. That's about it. Is that something that this board wants to do?
>> Furthermore,
I would just add one of the first thing that we should do is highlight it. This is happening.
People need to turn out
and vote.
You know, even if we don't take a firm position, yeah, or nay, although I actually am supportive on taking a nay position,
even if we want didn't want to go that far.
The the you know,
as Luis said, you know, they they kind of are you in the situation where you're kind of almost sneaking this thing in.
It's it's unlikely to be a high turnout election
and or referendum rather.
And that's my main concern is that you can get this thing passed with terrible verdict voter turnout, and we're stuck with it.
Right.
>> Yeah, judging by past referendums,
you know, you might get 100 votes total
in the town.
>> Right, which is absolutely atrocious. And this is my point. We need to, if anything,
the the biggest thing we could do is highlight it. I think the average end of our voter,
if they were activated and engaged, would look at it and probably see it more or less as we are, not everyone, but, you know,
and our position on whether it's a good idea or not, you know, again, I am supportive of taking a position, but the number one thing for me is trying to get people to raise the awareness.
Right.
If everyone
recalls Go
>> ahead. If everyone recalls, there's a lot of history regarding this
field project. They tried this a few years ago
and it, it failed and they come right back,
as Joanne mentioned,
right after the, very hard budget season for all three towns,
to tell you the truth.
Having, having, gone through the RAM School System myself,
my wife, my two sons,
and eventually my grandson,
it's just it's bad, bad time.
It's the same players that,
presented last time that now are are charging this thing right through with the help of
superintendent Leslie.
I personally think the part of finance should take a stand
and, you know,
as a group and, basically,
nix the whole project because
we have other things in this town to worry about besides, another $70,000
tax bill to the town every year,
till this thing is paid up. Where does it end?
>> That's my take on the whole thing. Right. Because then we're gonna have to replace it after the. Correct.
>> And I
listened to each presentation,
listened to our Board of Selectmen's presentation, their
presentation and discussion
and everything else.
I agree with
especially Scott Britton. I mean, the the you can mitigate the
drainage issues. And if you look at what the Hebron Public Works has done to those fields,
they're they're pristine.
The Ram
Ram,
fields and the Town Of Hebron fields
and our soccer field,
are are in pristine condition.
If you can mitigate the drainage situation at that football
field that they wanna make into a, coliseum,
fine.
But, you know, there's nothing better than it. I
I've I've looked at the studies of hurt fields and things like that, and,
athletes, especially real good athletes, are prone to injuries,
a lot more on a turf field than they are a grass natural field. So,
just my thoughts, and
>> I'm, I'm voting no. So Yeah. I I'm supportive of the board taking a firm position on this if you guys are. I'm with you.
>> Absolutely. I think we should. I think we I don't think if we try to, we can either write letters to the River East like we do.
But I think I'm in favor too. I think we really have to just say what we said here, which makes common sense.
Who usually when we do do a letter, who usually drafts that? Is it is there one person? Does it come from Mark as the
head?
Well.
>> Yeah, it would it would likely come from the chairman, I would think. Right.
But I was just
>> a letter isn't going to change anything that's still going to rough random. Right. So our issue. We know. So I I don't mind making a stand. Yeah. Is getting the public aware
so people come out and vote. Even if Vandover votes it no, if Marlborough doesn't come with us, even if Marlborough does come with us and say no, I don't know if we still have votes to override Hebron.
So, you you got two counts.
Typically in the- Yeah,
>> it's huge in Hebron right now. They they're all they're gathering their their votes for sure. Yeah. Right. Typically in the past it's always been that if Andover and Marlboro mobilize
>> sufficiently we can block Hebron but it it always has to be
you know, both towns in agreement.
Otherwise Hebron gets what it wants.
>> Oh,
I don't know. So here's what I'm throwing an idea out there. Instead of writing a letter to the
RAM Board of Ed, which really won't do anything for us, just put us officially on. Why couldn't we do some kind of flyer from the town to all of our town people,
you know, timing it
close enough to the election. Do you know what I mean? To say, are you aware?
>> Please vote. This is important. Right. Great idea. I I I think if we were to send a a flyer around to town, I think we'd have to be neutral on the ultimate question.
But the awareness,
>> I don't know, maybe I'm wrong about this Why do we have to be neutral if we're all against it?
So the first thing I don't I don't have a reason to be neutral if I'm against it. So I just was wondering.
>> So the thing you can do is you can put a letter directly in
the
River East,
and it's completely appropriate for the Board of Finance to write a letter to the River East,
you know, expressing
their desire to
not
pass this, if that's what you choose.
And it's also perfectly
fair to post that on the town social media site.
You know,
that that's,
that's an opinion from
the finance board of the town of Andover.
So you have the right to post that, you know, if you so choose.
I suppose if you really wanted to send it to every resident in the town, you could. Why not? It's just a mailing.
Okay.
>> I think you just have to be visible and vocal
and more or less involved.
I mean, truthfully, that's how I got involved in the town matters and the Board of Finance was just being present,
learning,
listening.
So that's all I was going to say, Robert. I understand the neutral thing. I didn't mean to come on so strong. I just mean,
I don't think it's such a bad idea to post
some reasons why we don't think it's a good idea.
I mean, that's and then asking who drafts it,
I have no problem starting to put something together and then passing it over for everyone to look at and add opinions.
I wouldn't be able to work on that till October, though. But which is and then so that's I just was wondering procedure.
>> Tommy, I can't remember any letter ever going out before since I've been involved. So
I don't have the history that Rob has and Kurt has, you know,
>> in this. Yeah. I mean, honestly, I don't know that I can recall us taking that step and my hesitance,
you know, may not be really well founded, guys. You know, this might be me being unwilling to take my own side in an argument.
I don't know why I'm speechless about it, but that said, no, and and it was for some reason the direct mail idea is the one that that
bothered me and the idea of putting a thing in the River East is fine with me and these are not really consistent positions. So
I'm just gonna go ahead and say,
fine.
Let's do that. Let's start working up a draft.
Let's
pass it around.
You know, Mark's not here tonight, but he, you know, he's gonna need to look at it, right?
And
but in general,
the idea of the Board of Finance flat out saying that this is, we think this is a bad idea for our town. I'm on board. So, forget my quibbles about the process or whatever.
Let's work on that. We have a little bit of time. We we're gonna wanna get that out there in advance of the election. You said it's you know, the referendum, which is in the first week of November. So
we've got, like, a month, basically,
to get this publicized.
>> Yeah, if I'm gonna work on a draft, it will definitely be in October. I've got some big things coming up and I'm happy to start putting it together and then sharing it with all of you.
And then if it's too much, and I mean, yeah, then we should do that. And then maybe, like you said,
third week of October
would be to start getting it in people's heads, then the voting is at the beginning of November.
Yeah.
Alright.
>> Personally,
I I feel that
I was just taking a stand that we're in favor of the project
and advertising
that fact either through the River East or
an article where every every townspeople sees it, I I really think that's about as far as we can really go,
to to draft a letter and everything else. I mean, just you know, we there's a lot of people in town, I'm sure, that are in favor.
Those that have two way kids, that that will be using the field and things like that. So,
but I I do think that just just taking the stand that we do,
and hopefully the board has slept into the same based on what I've heard, you know, listening to their meetings.
Then the townspeople need to make up their own decision when it comes to the referendum.
It's a ways off, so, a lot of people will forget,
if we were to write something. So that's my thoughts.
>> Yeah, we want to get that in there, you know, more or less right before the election to get to get people aware and involved in, you know, not have it fade.
>> If you want a chance of of
opposing it, should start now and start doing it vocally.
Without doing it,
you know, you're going to have to go big if you want a chance of preventing this from happening.
That's my sense.
Okay.
I agree.
>> Okay.
So,
all right. So
when you say that,
what are you thinking? You're thinking multiple letters? Are you thinking we put this in the River East every week? You know, that kind of thing. What you thinking, Aaron?
>> Yep.
Yeah. I'm thinking flying over all three towns with a plane going banner.
And wavering. Wait.
Wait. Wait. What's the budget on that, buddy?
Eric's gonna donate it. Yeah. If and
>> I think it's right, though, because then you're gonna get one letter out,
say, maybe the beginning of October,
and then you're going to get the people in favor. So they're going to start writing their letters.
Yeah, so it would be interesting.
And then hopefully you have people join
the not in favor side only because we want our money to go to other things, not because it's a bad thing.
>> It's just where you're spending the money and what you're gonna use it for. That's all. Yeah. And I mean, honestly, really, my take for what it's worth is that we hammer on the point that we could barely pass a budget this year for our own town.
Yeah. Okay. You and I may have a disagreement
about our budget priorities or what our budget should have been this year.
But putting that completely aside,
if $70,000
comes out
you know, for the next decade,
that makes all those discussions harder.
>> Well, the other thing I think that's worth thinking about is that
thinking about it in terms of the overall mission creep towards athletics.
Because remember, this is also a Ram Board of Education
that has decided
they're not going to charge any student activity fees anymore.
So they're not going to recover any of the costs from athletics for the students.
And it's also a group that has fairly recently in the last three years decided we couldn't possibly run a high school without a full blown athletic director,
you know, all while enrollment is dropping like a rock.
Yeah, I mean, personally, I think they're,
you know, they're prioritizing
athletics,
You know, in a very tough budgetary
climate.
To me that hurts.
You know, that hurts the core mission of the school which is education.
So I'm certainly not for it,
I mean.
>> Good point, Eric. They're just not, I mean, I think we all know how we feel. It's
just not a reasonable budget for the millions of emails and all the stuff that we talked about it's not so
hopefully
I agree with you I don't I think hope if we have to vote or whatever we have to do but I know we talked a lot last we last meeting
it's just not a good use of money right now and you're right thank you for bringing up the enrollment which is almost in half
so I mean how much longer you know how many teams and all of that are gonna
yeah.
Again, I like athletics.
>> My kids played sports, but I wouldn't be in favor of this. I got two kids that are gonna be going into Ram, and I'm perfectly happy to say no to this,
you know, and, you know, my girls play sports, But
this is nuts.
>> Let's let's build up our own recreation athletic
department here in Andover.
>> To the extent that makes sense. Yeah. You know my
daughter plays soccer right now. It's in, it's actually in Hebron.
You know, we use their fields. They have a great set. They have a wonderful set of fields
over at Burnt Hill.
That's great.
This is,
again, we're balancing priorities here. This is what we do. Every budget cycle, we do this. We have a finite amount of funds that we can use for certain things. And if you take 70 ks off the top right off the start,
it just it's gonna put pressure on everything else.
>> Do we wanna make a formal motion
to draft a letter and then see where it goes at the next meeting? And
obviously I'd like to get some input from Mark and, you know, move it. I was gonna say, I'd like to hear from Mark.
I
don't know if it needs a form of motion. I don't know if it's just something to say, you know,
>> put it on the agenda. Why don't we put it on the agenda, Diane? I think that makes sense. Let's just put it on the agenda for the next meeting.
>> And
Joanne, if you, you know, said you wanted to take a stab at a draft and maybe, you know, take October to kind of of before the next meeting and maybe we can kind of have something to have talking points around.
>> Yeah, I just have a,
my son's getting married in the next couple of weeks, so my focus is going to be there. But then beginning
of the month,
we start drafting it and then sharing it around.
Okay. Congratulations
to your son.
Gonna have a wedding this year so yay!
>> Yep I hear that like a family wedding coming up in October that's basically almost like a makeup because we had a wedding last year that most of the guest lists had to be struck from so
I hear you. Exciting
>> times, but stressful, you know, but happy,
really happy everyone
survived
the pandemic and all of that. Thank you. So right after, you know, beginning of October,
I'll draft something.
Okay, thanks. Okay,
>> just for the record.
If you wait to the next meeting,
you're already too late.
The next meeting is the October
27.
The referendum
is the second. So you've missed any deadlines for any publications.
You've missed any possibility of doing a mailing.
So if you're going to do it, you cannot wait till the next meeting, you're going to have to make a decision and work on it, you know, as a group between now and then,
or else,
you know, you probably just shouldn't bother.
>> Maybe
we should talk about, maybe we should have a try to to schedule a short special meeting
early October.
By the way, the twenty seventh you said? That's correct. Next Board of Finance meeting
is October
27.
>> Oof, okay. I was thinking the twentieth. All right.
Yeah,
you're right. That's way too close. Why
>> don't we just take a
vote tonight if somebody wants to make a motion
on where we stand on this entire project?
>> Right. Then wing it from there. But wait, I mean if we're gonna approve a letter, think
I agree to you like in terms of our intent, think we're all clear on this point. But
approving a letter I think requires I don't know whether we need a meeting or if we can just pass it around.
>> I'm not I'm not I'm not I'm not a big fan of sending out a letter personally. Just said that before when I talked. I think we to take it a board
and that will get out that the town of Andover Board of Finance basically, you
know, does not support the, you
know, the new Ram athletic fields and then just get that out to the voters. Well, how do we get that out then?
I'm sure it'll be reported in the River East. That's for sure.
>> My thought Kirk was not going to be a huge like official letter.
Mean, getting
our point, you know, something to the something to the effect, I don't want to
prompt it into the ground just because I have so much going on, I might not right
now, but just a little letter to the
editor,
blah, blah, blah, pointing out how this all came about.
It's kind of unfair after
a very busy,
tough
budget season to
have this project just come off and never moving on. I mean, I will make sense.
I don't see what's wrong with just drafting something, showing it to all of you,
not sending it without any. And then if we like it, and if we feel like it could move, putting it in the rib or niece or whatever we're gonna do, maybe then we could throw them together like
the tenth or something. Don't even have a calendar.
>> Oh, then again, then again, Mark, Mark is our, is our chairman and everything, everything that we do should go come, you know, should come through him.
So I would like to get his
>> his taken. I mean, would have to come up with some kind of quick draft. Right. And then
on the phone with Mark in a couple of weeks and see, get his time. Yeah.
And then see where it goes from there. Does that work for people? We don't have a lot of time.
>> Yeah. Well, listen, I'm the busiest lady on the planet. And if I'm willing to draft the letter, not on the planet, sorry. But right now I've got a lot of irons in the fire and working like a ton. But
if you all don't want that, then that's fine. I'm
willing to put in the effort even in my busy schedule.
I'll have a meeting in a couple of weeks then I'll save my time for something else.
If Kurt doesn't want to do that.
So
Well is not on our side.
>> Does anybody know when Mark is back? Is he back next week? Or is he still Listen, I have a wedding next week, so I can't do it next week, but I'm willing to be the most Just for me to be able to pick up the phone and call him and give him a heads up what's going on. That's all. I mean, that's that's whatever you all decide.
>> But, I mean, I would have drafted something after the wedding,
show it to all of you,
of course, going to Mark. Like, if he doesn't like the idea, you could all tell me, forget it. He's not in. And then I save my time for other stuff.
I would never disrespect the chairperson. I just know how these things take time.
>> Right.
And so I'm just looking at the calendar.
And if we are willing to circle back for a short meeting on, say,
the thirteenth,
maybe we could do that
a Wednesday earlier in October
so we can get this
off the ground. If if between now and then,
there's a conversation with Mark and Mark's not hot to trot on the idea,
then maybe we we nix the whole thing. But
maybe we could throw something on the calendar
so that we can reconvene and say, we all approve or don't approve of this
idea of this draft
that, you know, you're proposing that you're going to write, which is awesome.
And, you know, instead of waiting to the end of the month, which is too late. So, you know, I don't know that we can,
functionally we can do this without getting together again is my point.
>> I think that's a great idea. And that's all I like to do is have a date in mind because
when you're balancing a lot of things as you do too, yeah that's perfect to me. You need a deadline.
>> I definitely need a deadline. I completely understand this which is why I'm looking at a calendar.
>> Perfect. Could you think that may be a problem because isn't the thirteenth like
the board of select meeting the board of Ed meeting isn't there a bunch of meetings on that date in the town calendar already? Won't know Is
>> there sorry I'm looking at my phone. I'm not looking at the Because of the holiday because of Columbus Day. I think so. Oh, okay. Thirteenth
>> is already the Board of Education and the Board of Selectmen.
Okay. That's not gonna work. Alright.
So the Zoom accounts are taken up.
Okay,
let's,
calendar.
>> There's nothing on the twelfth. That's the Tuesday.
You can probably do it on the twelfth. The twentieth is too late.
Yeah. You could probably do it on Wednesday the sixth, but that is Nope, that's too early for market. Joanne, right? Yeah, that's too early, but I could definitely do the twelfth.
>> I just I think, again,
we know that we're going to be up against it. It's our one shot, you know. We're going to maybe write that letter, and then you're going to see follow-up letters in the two weeks after that.
So I'm for that, I'd be for the twelfth, but it depends There's on who
>> the twelfth and the fourteenth,
there's a meeting building
committee, but that's it at
seven. So the only thing I'd throw out there is, you know, I can, if we needed to do it on the twelfth,
I might be late. I I have right now my daughter has soccer practices on on Tuesday nights and they tend to end at seven in Hebron
so
>> I can try to make it. I can try to chime in in advance. You guys could start without me or something like that. If it has to be the twelfth, the twelfth is fine. I'll I'll make it work. Just. Fourteenth is fine too. I mean, don't know what other what the other members and I hope you guys all know when I said I'll find something else with my time. I didn't mean like leave the board of finance. I just in
>> my life, you know? No, I knew what you meant. Work or family. You wanna put a tentative meeting on the calendar for October 14 at 7PM?
I'm good with that if everyone else is.
>> I'm good with that. Even though I'm supposed to be in the other meeting, but you know what? Ed can So
>> Ed can run that meeting without me. And Diane, you're gonna run it by Mark, right? That we would do that. I'll
>> try and give Mark a call next week. I'm hoping he's back.
That sounds like a plan. Yep. Alright.
>> So
let's do that. Can we put a tentative meeting on the calendar, Amanda?
The fourteenth at 7PM?
Yeah, absolutely.
And I will
put it on my to do list. Will call Mark next week. I'm I'm assuming he will be back in town.
And
then if he's against it, then we'll just cancel the meeting.
Okay.
Did you say at 7PM?
Yes.
Thank you. All
>> right.
Yay. Okay. Eight B,
Board of Ed request letter regarding the
non lapsing account putting their surplus in the non lapsing.
Let me kind of bring you up to date with where we are. The letter that we got is kind of pretty generic
and it says, you know, up to 2%,
approximately $50,000
Where I'm sitting on this right now, and I did talk with Valerie Brunel
last night as well,
I would feel better from a process and transparency
point of view. I have no problem
personally on my, I'm not going speak for the board. I'm giving surplus into nonmath back to the school.
I just want to wait
until the school
year budget is closed out and everything's accounted for and we have an exact dollar amount. I think we should be making this decision knowing what the exact dollar amount is.
Absolutely. We'll move to the next meeting. I agree.
I agree. Does everybody have any different opinion on that? With pushing this off until October?
There's no urgency right now. You know, the money's not going anywhere.
>> Right.
That seems reasonable enough to me. Agree. What did Val say when you chatted with her, Diane? What did she have any issue with that? No. No. She does. No. I've talked to her as well. Yeah. She doesn't have an issue at all. Right. No. That should be fine though. So I
>> will go on the record to make a motion to take table this until the next meeting in October.
>> Do I have a second for that? The just to clarify this, the regular meeting. Yeah. Regular meeting. Yep.
Second.
Any more discussion on this?
All
in favor?
Aye.
Aye. Aye. Anonymous.
Okay.
Excavator.
>> Alright.
I'm gonna share my screen again here real quick. I didn't mean I can do this successfully.
Alright, so
we went back to the manufacturer
and clarified.
Okay let me back up and say at this point, both the Board of Selectmen
and
CIP
are in agreement with the purchase of an excavator.
So,
presuming that you all agree.
The question,
there's two questions to be answered.
Presuming you agree. The first question is whether you want to
do it as a sixty month loan,
number one, or whether you want to buy it outright in the case of the excavator.
And the secondary question is going to be,
do you want to
the
one member of the Board of Selectmen was adamant that you could take this out of town Aid Road.
And
>> the rest didn't really have an opinion on it. So the two questions to answer are where you want the funding source for this to be, And whether you want to
do it as a, you know, a five year loan,
or whether you want to just purchase the thing outright. So those are really the questions.
So,
to
just to where
we are, we've been renting this thing
now for about three months.
The total cost.
So the first two months of rental can be applied 100% due to cost of purchase a machine,
the third month of rental
75%
of it can be
applied to the cost.
So the outright purchase cost of the machine
was 96,135.
There is a rental credit at this point of 11,756,
which leaves a residual payment of $84,378.75.
And they say we got to pay a document processing fee of $300.
So the total is $84,000
And
they are not offering.
So, this is where it annoys me a little bit because they to me get a little scammy
that this purchase cost
includes
a 12%
additional
municipal discount.
If
they offer 0%
interest
>> loans,
but they don't give us the 12% they don't give us the,
you know, 12%
municipal credit if they do, which is kind of bullshit, but the bottom line is,
if we were to use their financing
for a sixty month loan
interest payment would be 4.05%,
would bring the total purchase price to 93,680.
So, we would be paying a total of $9,310
interest using their figures.
So that's really the question.
You know,
to me, I
don't like paying interest, so I'd opt to purchase it outright, but that's not my decision. That's kind of your decision.
>> I don't like interest either. Here's my question for you. You mentioned earlier that the Select board talked about where the money can come from.
And there was some,
I don't know if I could say disagreement,
but you know, can are they is the one to select number, right? That it's going to out of town road.
>> So if your question is, can legally we spend town road money to purchase a piece of equipment that's used for maintaining roads? The answer is yes.
So
it is, we are perfectly we're not breaking any laws to do that.
And if you
just to give you both the current balances.
The current balances in the town aid road account
as of today is 104,145.
So that's with them having paid us or on or August
installment.
The record, you can see before that we had drawn that account all the way down to around $10,000
doing roadwork this year.
The problem is is that if you take,
you know, 90 something thousand dollars
from town aid road,
that is $90,000
less you have to spend, you have available for next year's roadwork.
Yep.
And we use the balance
from this year
to fund and do a lot of spring work because oftentimes it's cheaper to hire the contractors before the new fiscal year.
You know, so we do a lot of work in May, June,
you know, April, May, June with the contractors so
I mean we could take it out of town Aid Road.
To me, that's the whole reason why we have a public works capital equipment fund is to fund purchase of equipment
for public works.
But, you know, so the answer to your question is you could take it from that if you so chose,
>> Or you just,
yeah, I see your problem with it and I don't disagree at all.
What do we have in our
capital budget for equipment?
We Put
>> it in this budget year. Yeah. Added a 100 k, but what do we have for a balance?
Our total balance is $113,888
including
>> the 100 ks we're putting in this year. Oh, I see it now. I'm sorry. It's right at the bottom there. So if we did this,
we'd have like 30,000 left.
If this is 84,
you said 84 and a half, something like that, you'd be at a little less 30.
Well, plus 12 for the compactor.
>> Oh God. Okay.
So,
all right. So you put, you're spending almost 100 here.
Correct.
Right. Yep.
>> So that would more, it would almost wipe that out.
We'd be down to, you know,
14,000 or something like that. If off the top of my head.
Yep. 15,000.
Okay.
>> Just theoretically
if you wanted to split the difference.
You could
purchase the loader or the excavator
from public works equipment and you could purchase the.
What do you call it, the compactor from Downey Road, if you thought that was appropriate. Yeah,
>> but I mean the capital budget exists for a reason. Yeah, I'm really, I'm kind of leaning where you were leaning, which is this is why we have a capital budget.
>> The
price of the compactor is
below the dollar threshold, what we call capital equipment.
It's 15,000 and up.
So it probably should come out of town a road.
Okay,
I hadn't done it that way, Diane.
Only because I read that purchasing policy today that.
Serves you right for
doing that.
Too much information.
>> Diane,
can I comment? Yes.
And I'll ask Eric and maybe even Rob. What happened between last Thursday night or at capital improvements meeting versus tonight?
>> I I think we're gonna get to the process issue later. Would you agree, Eric?
Yeah. I I
>> thought how do you how do you figure that one off?
>> This I was gonna do that in liaison, but okay. We can bring it up now. We should bring it you know what? Let's just do it now. Please go ahead. Okay, so
not to throw a huge wrench in the works, everybody, but we had our CIP meeting and
it was brought up to us at that time that
this whole purchase
plan kind of happened outside of CIP.
It was, you know, the the board of selectmen
decided this needed to be done and it was not run through CIP. CIP hadn't had a chance to review it. We did talk about it at our meeting and nobody thought it was crazy or anything, but there was a little bit of frustration and concern
that it had not gone through what we considered to be kind of proper channels in terms of if you have a capital improvement committee
and you're going to make capital purchases,
why were they not consulted?
We got consulted at the absolute eleventh hour.
So although I don't think I've seen it yet, there was a decision made that the chairperson
of the capital improvement committee would be sending an email or something along those lines to both the select board and the Board of Finance to
ask for some clarity on the process here and and and just sort of question why this wouldn't hadn't
been
brought before the CIP before it was brought before everybody else make a final decision.
That said,
I don't think we had an issue with the substance of the
the proposal. In other words, I don't think we sat down there and said that these numbers are unacceptable,
that this isn't a reasonable idea.
It was all about the process.
And I don't think anybody at CIP was really willing to
try and hold this thing up on principle. We just wanted to put it out there that going forward
we
I think CIP should probably be involved.
Do
you think that's a fair summation Kirk? Because you were there too.
>> Well, I
need to add the fact that this basically goes against our charter,
that the charter which states what the CIP's
job is,
you know, to give recommendations to the Board of Select, the Board of Finance.
And it also violates the
the person policies that I read, in regards to bids or RFPs.
You know, it's a, it's a, it's a very expensive item.
There's many companies that, that build this unit.
We've we've, we've rented them,
you know, before
in town for specialized work, which is what they did with this one.
But I think it totally
it totally.
Does it it it goes against the, you know, the Charter and the, and the, what the CIP was was was,
you know, was made to do,
I. E. The, you know, just just go back in in in the last purchases,
the banker truck for $414,000
that went to RFP,
and the low the low the low bid was accepted
on that. Any anything that the fire fire department,
goes out to goes out to an RFP
and all, you know, and they
CFP requests at least three bids
or or three RFPs on each individual item. So this totally goes against everything and for the Board of Selectmen to approve it
without any, input from the capital improvements,
you know, and also violating basically what the charter states on the amounts,
of of different equipment,
costs,
that needs to go to bid. It's just I don't I don't buy it. And I I made that statement clear at the Capital Improvements meeting the other night. So I just the letter the letter that Fred sent, I'm sure he sent it, but it went to Mark as chairman of the board of finance.
And as you see, Mark, you know, Mark's away. So that's why it didn't get probably, you know, read into tonight's
agenda.
But,
that's just just my thoughts again.
You know, it's it's it's basically,
totally
usurping the entire,
capital improvements committee and the, charter.
>> Let me ask a question.
Didn't we get this pricing through a government sourced
kind of
because there's a carve out for purchasing part to be sufficient to fulfill the bids and the purchasing. Did we get this price through that? You can you can, I don't if the town had gone through the, ct.gov,
>> the state of Connecticut purchasing,
you know, the purchasing,
consortium, basically?
Sourcewell was used on, on, on our last dump trucks that,
that the town purchased.
You know, there's, HDAC
is another consortium out there that a bunch of municipalities use,
but you basically, you get, you get the state,
the state bid on any piece of equipment that you're after, whether it be a, an excavator, a fire truck, a police cruiser,
you know, a vehicle for the, for the building inspector if you were to buy one, things like that. The state has a, an actual bid list for this, and you can advertise it on the state bid list at no cost.
And that gives, that gives a chance for everybody out there that, supplies this type of equipment
to submit their bid. There's many, trust me, there's many, many people or, you know, companies that that, that construct excavators. Excavators. We happen to be using this one, it was brand new,
because they needed to rent it for the drainage work on
Shottie Mill, no question.
But
to go and purchase it and have it come through the Board of Selectmen and say, yep, you can take it out of this, take it out of that
without the board of, or the Capital Improvements Committee, number one, not even knowing it and basically going against the Charter as it's written right now.
It just doesn't cut it far as I'm concerned.
>> So realistically,
we didn't get three bids,
public bids on this. No. I mean, we have charged other people for not getting three bids.
>> So, he did supply multiple
bids
for
equipment
with the packet.
The one we are selecting
that is
that is their basically their state bid price is what we're,
you know, we're paying.
You're right, it did not go to RFP I'm not going to tell you it did because it did not.
The question
though is that,
you know, so so let me go back and say that the first thing that happened is,
is we had a discussion with CIP in the spring,
about the purchase of a larger size excavator.
And the CIP
was not interested in,
in even really hearing it or discussing it in the spring, which is okay, that's the right.
So,
we
rented
the piece of equipment that we rented,
because
I sent Jay out and I said go find out what all the other towns are using,
you know, and go try them out, see whether they'll let you try them.
So that's what Jay and Tommy did. We sent Tom because he's our normal equipment operator out.
And they tried a couple different units that other municipalities
used.
Because the real question is, is can we get one small enough that we can tow it
with our existing trucks without buying a new trailer,
yet big enough to do most of the drainage work we need to do. So that's really why they settled on the machine they settled on,
because
it seems to be a fairly common unit in use by other municipalities.
And it's the right size.
And it's one of the few dual piston units in this size
that has the oomph to
do it. So they tried it with Mansfield.
And then, you know,
they first we first demoed it, we had the company drop one off.
And they took it out to the pit.
And they dug a bunch of holes with it rotated it through all the operators and said, can it do what we expect it to do? And the answer was yes.
So they,
you know, leased it for the summer for the drainage work.
You know, and the, the,
you know, because we didn't have approval to buy it before.
So, but the problem
is, is that,
you know, you're sucking up $4,000
a month to rent this thing to use.
So,
you know, one of the things we looked at was if we were going to rent it, if we decided that was a machine we wanted,
could we recoup that cost
if we purchased that machine?
And the answer from them was yes, if you buy it within the period that you're leasing it, we will apply most of that cost to the purchase.
So that's kind of where how we ended up
where we are.
You know, we can certainly look at other machines at this point
and go back and do an RFP,
but we're
going to lose,
you know, a fairly significant,
you know, somewhere in $12,000
worth of rental that we're not going to be able to apply to the purchase.
So I think that's why Board of Selectmen
was
on board with it. Because if you go back and relook at it now,
now you have to be looking at a machine
in order to equal your cost. You got to get something that's $12,000
cheaper than this,
which was unrealistic.
>> Eric, a quick, just to clarify,
at what point do we lose the ability to apply
the rental money,
that 12,000 or so toward the purchase price of this particular machine?
>> So we originally had a four month rental on it and we're in month
three. We haven't paid for month four yet.
So we could go another month if you wanted
to make a decision.
>> Right. But at the end of that fourth month,
if we haven't agreed to purchase this machine,
we sort of forfeit that discount. Is that correct? Yes.
>> If we send it back to them and it gets rented out with somebody else, we've lost the ability to
to just to piggyback
and own it.
>> So
that's the practical consideration.
You know, not that anything Kurt said was wrong. I I think he's
right.
It's just,
you know, at the same time you're talking about the practical fact that, you know,
unless we got a really good price from somebody else, I mean, we can bid it out. How long would the bid process take?
>> Months? But
if we went through the consortiums that it talks about
in the purchasing documents,
we wouldn't have to do the public bids. We could go there
and eliminate that step.
>> So
so there's two things. One,
I apologize, the governing section
in the charter
is section eight zero seven.
If you want, I can bring that up and you can read that, then it refers to this purchasing policy, right, basically, the, the charter
says that the Board of Finance needs to come up with a purchasing policy.
So it really
dates back to the purchasing policy.
You know, and you've got to decide whether you want to abide by your own purchasing policy or,
you know, you want to do something else I think this does technically meet the requirements
of the purchasing policy,
because the cost
for the machine is established,
you know, through the state bid process,
or through the original state,
municipal,
whatever you call that.
You know, it's not the one for the other
for the compactor is a source well quote,
which we also accept or we have in the past anyway.
>> So I'm going to read this section because it says the use of state of Connecticut
or other government
cooperative purchasing program shall be considered sufficient to fulfill the requirements of this part. And this is the part of talking about going out to RFP.
So if we get
through that cooperative and get a price there, we do not have to do the formal
bidding process.
>> Correct? That is correct.
Per the policy you have written now.
>> So
if what we have now
meets that requirement,
I'm okay with not doing all the other stuff because it's within our policy. I'm not in favor of going outside of our policy until we
rewrite it because our policy is our policy
and what we have now.
So I guess
>> I was hoping I could just say that I
our
town has gotten in a little bit of trouble through the years since I've been here, fifteen years for not following procedure
and process.
I
just want to state, appreciate
Kurt coming forward with that
and just talking about proper procedures
and processes.
Sheri's dealing with it now.
Sherry's
doing
I
agree to save money wherever we can, but I feel like month after month at these meetings, are we just gonna justify everything that's done?
And I that's hard for me to stand behind too I get saving money and needing the equipment
but if we don't and and I'll be I will not talk long on this but
the very core
is you know following the procedures that's what I do in my job all day is you know in
hr and with people and you know in a school is we have to follow the process and the procedure
Everyone wants to cut corners.
And I don't always think that, Okay, so we save money, so it's Okay. Okay, so next month,
this person did this job in two hours, so he didn't have to work a full day. I don't know where we cut the
where we stop following process and proceed. I'm not advocating not following our purchasing. No, that's just my point. I just wanted to back up Kurt in this and I really appreciate it. No, no, I get you.
>> Want
to make sure
I don't want to continue to rent a machine
we need to buy and waste money there. I really don't wanna lose.
No, that's the end. I get it. I get it. So I wanna comply with the policy.
If So our quote falls into that exemption
for these government consortiums,
then we don't have to go to public bid and we're done.
>> Right. I I
think what we talked about at CIP was that this is
not necessarily technically
a violation
of our processes, but it's more it's it's a little bit of a gray area
and CIP not being involved
made us kind of uncomfortable with how this all went down.
But my take and I'll repeat it is that I think we should think about the process issues and do better next time. And at the same time, not necessarily hold up something
that is ultimately a good deal for the town.
That's my ultimate take on this, that we shouldn't just ignore procedure, correct? However, this one,
and I think as Eric has explained, it's a little bit,
you know, technically this, this can work.
It's just maybe not the best way we could have done it.
If that's a fair summation,
Eric.
>> Yeah, I would. And the other thing I would say is that when we started renting this,
we rented this with the full realization that we might not buy it.
And we might just spend $12,000
this summer,
you know, on a machine
to get the work done that we needed to do. So I mean,
you know, it's not like we, the town,
You know, we didn't
rent the thing.
Certain that we were going to then use that as the purchasing decision.
Rented it. And then,
you know,
and then brought it back to the boards to say,
well, given how much drainage work we have to do,
it doesn't really make financial sense to continue renting this thing every summer, because for what we're renting it, you know, in about five years we can own the thing. So we'd be smarter to buy it rather than to continue to rent it.
Oh,
>> I get the and I agree that everything should go through CIP,
but I'm looking for a document that says it has to go to CIP first because this purchasing policy doesn't even say that. Well, is for another discussion we had with Eric. Okay.
And the and the traveler says
refer to the purchasing
>> policy. Yeah. So It's a little circular, Diane, is the issue. And, you know, when we first drafted that purchasing, I was on the board when we drafted that thing. Okay.
That was our first cut
at having any kind of purchasing policy for this town.
I think we meant well, but I don't think we nailed everything down. And one thing that Eric brought up at the CIP meeting and I'm complete agreement with this is that maybe we need to tighten it up
and specify some some procedures.
Our main
concern when we drafted that thing
was that we weren't bidding out anything
necessarily.
Right. Right. We had nothing in place that
made us bid out anything.
And we had had a course of performance in this town
of going out and just, know, the first electman thought this was a good deal. And so it happened.
And we don't do that anymore. Thank goodness.
But at the same time, that purchasing policy could probably be better and more specific
about the steps
and who does what.
I think that's something
that we talked about CIP, and I do agree
that the purchasing policy could be reworked and made clearer as to exactly whose role is what.
And, know,
step one, step two, step three.
And I think that's something we should continue to kick around and improve upon.
At the same time, we have this thing in front of us.
And if we want if we do think this is a good idea, we have about a month to pull the trigger.
That's
my take.
>> I'm in agreement with all of that. I just wanna make sure that going forward, we don't see this in another
purchasing
thing. Know, a good deal is a good deal, of course,
but just kinda tighten it up and not not see the same thing in another meeting for another piece of equipment. We can't just ad hoc this stuff left and right. I completely agree with that.
>> I don't have a charter in front of me, but I think the charter states it used to be either 2,000 or $2,500
or more. Because
I printed it today. Is it it is it up to 5,000 now? $5,000
I think the board of finance set that amount.
So eight zero seven
says Incorrect.
>> Purchasing
that the Board of Finance in consultation with the CIP
and the Board shall establish and maintain written procedures and policies,
blah, blah, blah for purchasing.
So there is no
No set amount. No set amount.
>> No, it refers to the purchasing policy, does have set amounts.
>> The purchasing However Capital
is
$15,000
or more,
the
loader is the excavator, I mean, is
in that way. Correct.
But
>> it's not violating our policy if it meets the requirements of these general requirements on page four
that we're getting the price through a cooperative purchasing program, government cooperative purchasing program. And we don't have to do public bid. I just wanna make sure we're following our policy for this decision.
I know we need to clean this purchasing.
>> Diane,
what you need to understand is that every
major manufacturer
of excavators,
fire trucks, vehicles,
pencils for the school,
they they meet the
the,
you know, the consortium's
thing. They're they're they're all members of it.
You know, I I I deal with this every day,
in in my business of selling fire apparatus.
You know,
every major manufacturer,
my my own included,
belong to StorSwell,
because,
HGAC,
there's, there's
two or three others out there. Everyone
submits that same and follows that same purchasing procedures and pricing,
whether it be the state of Connecticut
or the state of Texas or the state of, Maine.
All the,
all 50 states in this country participate
in the, in these various consortiums
for buying municipal equipment.
So,
you're you're not I mean, yes, you know, you're buying from a company
that uses source well. Well, there's there's probably 50 or 60 other companies
that use source well and are and would be more than willing to submit a RFP or a bid to town of Andover for a brand new excavator of that size.
That that's that's the only thing I'm I'm I'm trying the only the only point I'm trying to make is, you know, we've we've done this
through the last,
half a dozen
pieces of equipment that were over $15,000
purchased next to Fort The Fire Station.
And I was able to get, you know, at least
three,
you know, general bids or RFPs
on each piece of equipment.
So that's that's, I think, part of the procedures.
And But our it's no question
>> has a carve out that you don't have to do public bids
if you go through these consortiums.
>> Yeah. But it's not a public bid. It's an RFP. It's a request for purchase.
There's a difference between an RFP and a bid.
>> Yeah, but there's a carve out that you don't have to do that if you go here.
>> That's what I'm saying. I'm very confused here. Yeah, but you can do that with any manufacturer.
>> So it says purchases made outside such brokers shall comply with the following requirements. And then it goes through the public big documents of what the requirements are. But if you're within those consortiums and you're buying through those, you don't have to do all that.
>> That's how I'm reading it. Yeah. Well, I I still feel if we if we go through this purchase without sending it out to everybody,
we're, we're setting a precedent. That's all.
>> Which is fine. So, Diane, you are in that the current purchasing
policy
allows us
to use any of the cooperative bidding services
such as Sourcewell
to
establish the price instead of going and putting out our own RFP.
Because essentially it's just like the the salt bid, you know, for Kroger any of these other organizations,
it is a competitive bidding process. We're just,
you know, we're just not putting the bid out ourselves,
we are putting the bid out, We are using somebody else's bid.
Great cooperative buying agreement.
>> So
here's my deal.
I do not wanna violate our policy.
And I'm just asking for assurances because Kurt's reading this a different way that we should be getting bids. And I'm trying to say, are we fitting within this general requirements exemption
>> until we clean up the process better. And if we decide later that that exemption is too broad, we can fix it. Right. I guess what I'm saying, I'm
>> not in favor of violating our policy
at all.
I just want to make sure we're within it.
You are within your purchasing policy as written
>> to buy this as it feels differently so I guess I'm trying to understand how court is reading Curtis
>> thinks
we could do better.
Not that what we're doing doesn't meet our actual policy would be my guess or
You're muted, sorry.
>> No, they're
they're they're throwing a bone that they're going to,
they're gonna put the rental, the amount of,
of money we spend on rental towards the overall purchase. And that doesn't say that any other company, Caterpillar,
Kubota,
New Holland, there's million different manufacturers of that same size machine.
May not be spec exactly. I can't even pronounce the name of Eric, what's the name of this machine?
TakaoT or something like that. TakaoT.
>> I'm
questioning that it's not a good machine.
It's just the fact that that you've made other boards and commissions go through the process
of
going through capital improvements,
getting their approval first
and then moving it on to the Board of Selectmen and the Board of Finance,
you know, for their yes, yes or no,
in the in the procedures.
We followed it next door at the fire department, and I'm not trying to say that that that, you know, that we wouldn't follow it, but
I just think it's setting a precedent when when something comes along and they say, we'll we'll we'll we'll give you we'll give you a
but you would have rented it anyway.
Whether or not you're gonna purchase it. You know, personally, I think we need more people down there at town hall. I mean, the public works than we do another machine.
That that's just my opinion.
But, you know,
just just,
you know,
we we had this discussion Thursday night amongst everyone on that was there for the meeting cap improvements,
and, it's it's kinda like, you know, gotten off the rails. That's all.
>> Oh, I I understand
the position that things should go through CIP.
Okay, so in this case, it didn't do that.
Here we are with a decision on a price to purchase an excavator.
And I'm trying to determine if it's within our purchasing
policy, we're not violating a policy,
and we're getting a good price because of this rental credit
that we can't get. And I don't know if we can't get any. We haven't rented from anybody else. So nobody's going to give us a rented credit.
So.
Yeah, that that's kind of where I'm at too. I wanna make a good decision to be within policy.
>> If this is, if this squares with our policy, technically, even if we have our issues with it,
we can proceed
and then tighten up the process.
>> That's my where I've been coming at this all along. I mean, Kurt, do you think that you can get a better price?
>> That's
that's not that's not the point of a different price. You know, I'm I'm all for saving money. Trust me, Diane. I'm not I'm not against saving money. It's just the fact that the the process,
the the transparent process that we have in place right now
was not followed.
And and a board of selectmen,
made a decision over the board of finance
and the, capital improvements committee that it's okay to purchase this machine and get the get the discounts that we're gonna get. And don't forget, just a few months ago,
we we held the school
to task on their outdoor
classroom for x amount of thousands of dollars and basically said, you know, that- that never went through capital improvements or anything.
>> The school is not required to go through CIC. I understand that, but they still,
>> they- they did not- I don't see it being constructed. That's my point, you know, based- based on the the what we went through with them. So it's a basically
a point of order. Don't I don't know what you want to call it. It's just, you know, we the procedures
were not followed
properly
as they have been
recently in the past
so that's and I
>> agree with that can I ask Eric a question
just if I'm gonna vote on this how much work and I think it was said at other meetings how much work do we have lined up that requires this excavator
excavator?
>> I
mean, I'll be perfectly honest,
you know, we've identified
ten or twelve years worth of drainage projects we need to do.
Our limitation is strictly
manpower and hours we can actually do, because we have so many other things we're obligated to do. I mean, we got we didn't get a lot of drainage issues dealt with this year.
Because,
you know, we got stuck dealing with storm response.
But we also need to clean out all our waterways,
that would take us two or three months. And this is the obvious machine for doing that.
You know, there's no question,
we're going to use this thing.
And there's no question,
it's a very useful piece of equipment.
In the past, we have rented one
when we did projects.
We did not rent one last summer, but most summers public works ends up renting a machine for at least a period of time every summer.
We've just never
pulled the trigger and actually purchased one ourselves before.
>> That was a good answer. Mean, said you have you just said you have so, you've identified so much work that could be done. I mean, I know what they're used for. I know, I just wanted to make sure it wasn't just a year long thing.
I mean, clearly it can always be used or you can find use for it. But no. Thank you. You've answered my question if I'm gonna have to vote ultimately.
Thank you.
>> It's I don't I don't have a question on the need. You know? It's it's it's it's there's definite there's definitely a need for the machine.
And it's not not the Eric's fault or the public works department fault that the machine sat
on the side of road for two weeks due to the due to storms
the the storms that we had. You know, the machine literally sat there without being here.
I don't know, maybe
two weeks. I'm not I'm not positive on that, but that that's you can't help that because the let the the amount of manpower we have in public works is four guys. And and we've been intubated with three or four storms this this past
summer and, you know, spring, summer, and fall that have have taken, you know, these guys elsewhere.
So while it sits there and and we're still paying rentals on it, you know, they
should credit us for that, the time that it sat there, but they're not, but they're going to take it off the price. You know, understand all that too.
So
it's just the fact that, you know, to actually purchase it for the town of Andover,
I think it needs to follow the break procedures. That's all. Not not during a rental.
You know, you we're gonna rent it anyways if we need it or not.
So
>> And I understand, Kurt, that you're thinking they didn't follow procedure, but when I'm reading the document, I'm seeing that we are within our procedures, even though we don't like what they are and that somebody went outside of Well, that's fine. And
>> if I have to stand corrected, I'll stand corrected. But I just know what I've done in in the past couple of couple of three years,
you know, through the through the Board of Fire Commissioners.
And
and I and I I know, you know, I'm I'm comfortable in in the fact that we followed the town's procedures.
We fought for these procedures for a long time,
and up until this this new administration that we have, nothing was followed up until they come into, you know, they they came into fruition.
I'll I'll I'll leave it with I'll leave it at that. You know, it's it's it's up to the board, whatever you wanna do, that's that's fine with me.
>> Do we want to make a motion or does people want to discuss this more?
>> I I think we've discussed it enough, so it's you know someone should make a motion. Sat with discussion.
>> All right. So I'll stick my neck out and
I will put forth a motion
to approve the purchase of the excavator
as priced
with the rental discount
with the condition that we are not violating our purchasing
procedures
because we're going
in the carve out exemption
for cooperative purchasing programs.
And
with the added
caveat that going forward,
we will ensure that we're following the CIP process
and we will be looking at taking these purchasing policy and procedures and clarifying them better to make it more clear about what the expectations are.
>> Anybody think we need to add anything else to that? My only question is whether we need to specify where we're taking the money from.
You know, are are we agreed that we're taking this out of the capital equipment fund?
>> I think, and this is my opinion, I think the
excavator should come out of capital equipment and the
compactor out of Town Aid Road.
>> Okay, well, you know, I just think if we're doing this, we probably want to have that
agreed upon as well. So if that's your motion, then let's proceed
on that basis.
Do I have a second on that?
I'll go ahead and second it.
>> Any further discussion? Does anybody have anything else they wanna add?
Okay. All in favor?
Aye.
Aye. Aye. For me, Kurt.
I'm not I'm not an eye.
Figured that.
We have four yeses and one no.
I'm a no. Okay.
Fair.
Right.
Alright, motion passes.
>> So Amanda, can you read the motion back so we make sure we got the verbiage correct?
>> It's a little blurry. I'm gonna have to backtrack on that one.
I will try and remember what I said.
Kind of hard.
Okay, I wrote down the time of the recording.
>> Okay.
So the second part of that would be the purchase of the plate compactor.
To come out of Town Aid Road.
>> Were you was that original motion, did that cover both those pieces of equipment?
I thought the first motion was just for the
>> excavator. Was that wrong? I forgot. Well, I meant to include both pieces because that's what the whole thing is for. Right? And then when I asked for clarity,
>> you know, we were talking about where the money came from and and the clarification was that, you know, the larger piece of equipment was coming out of our capital fund and
the smaller piece of equipment was gonna come out of town a road.
So I understood it to be a two part motion covering both pieces of machinery. But
if if people wanna split it up, we can we could do that.
>> Okay.
Is everyone I meant to include both pieces.
Even though I only said excavator I didn't say compactor.
>> Diane, I think you did say compactor.
Oh, did I? I think so.
I think you got it, but Okay.
>> I'm okay with it with the added stipulation of doing better in the future, whatever that wording was.
>> Okay. And to put us
I'm gonna make another motion to put us and keep us all honest. I would like to make a motion
that the Board of Finance
will
be updating
the purchasing policy for the town of Andover to
add more clarity for the process that should be followed and the steps to be taken.
I don't know if anybody wants to make a section a second on that.
>> Sorry,
Diane.
I think we do need to revisit our policies.
>> And I just want to put it on record that we are going to go and update this policy so this doesn't happen again.
Agreed with that second.
Sounds good. All
in favor?
Aye.
Kurt, you an eye on updating the purchasing?
>> Yeah.
I'm an eye on that.
Yeah.
I'm an eye. Alright.
>> So,
Linda, you said aye. Right?
Okay.
I heard Joanne. Okay. So, all good.
All right. Did I do everything right?
>> Amanda's
rewrite recap
of motion
seem to only have
the larger machine in it. So
we may need to
make
a second motion with respect to the smaller machine.
>> Okay. I'll make a just to clear it, clean it up. I'll make a motion that the purchase of the compactor
for the amount submitted,
which was a source well bid, correct?
Correct. So
what was the amount again?
>> So it was a source well, the source well bid
for the new machine was 12,000
I think $500
But they
we have
we rented basically a used machine because we needed to compact the bridge. It's got about 100 and had about one hundred and forty hours on it. Now it's got about one hundred and sixty hours because we've been using it.
That machine,
they will sell to us for $9,500
We can purchase a brand new one. But given that we're we can purchase the rental unit with low hours on it for 9,500.
You know, we all decided saving
extra $3 would be it would be smarter to do that than to
then to purchase a new one. Oh, that's a good deal.
>> Okay.
So, so
the
motion to be amended
on the compactor is to purchase the used machine for 9,500.
Correct. For it out of Town Aid Road.
Okay.
Love it. Second it. Let's do it.
All in favor?
Aye. Nice.
>> Okay, that's unanimous.
Okay.
We
gotta do the hard stuff in the beginning, not at the end.
>> So let's get that purchase
policy revision thing high on the agenda, Hold
on. Haven't got to the road striping yet.
Oh, god. Oh, lord.
>> Alright. I think you can nix the road striping unless you have questions for us about it.
>> Did they run out of? Yeah, I do have a question. They run out of paint from Lakeview Drive to Route 6. They did run out of paint.
>> They will be back to finish. Okay, that's all I need to know. There was at least one extremely irate person with us for painting lines,
who left left me
a pretty astounding
expletive labeled,
you
know,
you know, thing on my answering machine
about his displeasure
>> at being woken up by the the roadwork at night. My neighbor down the street was it?
>> It was too incoherent.
Know, you could hear the f bombs, but it was hard to
tell what the other words are.
All the joys of public service error. His intent was pretty clear that he was unhappy with the night work though.
Okay.
>> Okay.
So we did that. We have this item on your credit card purchasing policy. I have no idea what that is.
>> So there's a copy of that in your packet.
So we
just tuned up our credit card purchasing policies a little bit, and came up with a couple of new forms. We're just giving you this I don't think the Board of Finance
necessarily
needs to approve this, But we just had a couple issues with the way things were being done.
So
we tuned up our procedures internally a little bit as a as a downfall.
And I think Sherry could give you more info on that. But I definitely agree with it.
Should be in your packet.
>> We don't need to make
any motions on it's just a form it's FYI information only. Correct.
Correct.
That's fine.
Moving on.
>> Hey.
Down here.
Okay.
We already talked about the purchasing policy made a motion to do that.
So how electrical upgrades.
>> So I talked about that in my report,
since the Board of Selectmen has decided to increase the scope. I'm not ready to ask
>> for anything on that right now. And that's all going through CIP, right?
>> As far as I'm concerned, that can go through CIP. We already we already sent the CIP last Thursday night. And
for the record, the initial
town hall electrical upgrades
was already approved by CIP.
Board of Finance decided that should go to RFP
a while back, and I finally got around to drafting the RFP.
But then the Board of Selectmen decided they wanted to take care of a bunch of other projects
as part of that. So it will go back to CIP and then come back to you. Right. It'll It'll have a larger proposal to deal with that. It'll be over 15,000.
Correct? Presumably.
>> Yep. Yeah. Okay.
Still
not that what we needed to do.
All right, H
>> affordable housing plan. You talked about that in your report, right? Yeah, I don't think as long as you guys have no objection to me signing for it, we don't need to discuss that further.
I added that in case you decided you wanted to make a motion or you wanted input in that.
>> All right.
Okay, now we're down to the approval meeting minutes can I have a motion to approve the meeting minutes from Wednesday, August 25?
Right, Kurt.
>> Kurt's muted but yeah, I think he said yes. Okay. Yeah, sorry about that. Yeah, I make a motion.
>> Okay. Any second.
Second it.
Okay, any discussion? Nope. All in favor?
Aye. Aye.
Okay.
Liaison reports.
>> Do we have So we basically dealt with CIP,
you know, that that was the the overwhelming
bit of the of our CIP meeting
last Thursday was the discussion of this,
you know buying this this excavator
so and the process that's good that's good yeah
we went through this and I think made our opinion on it plain
and I think that
to be continued in that
when Mark gets back the letter that no doubt our chairperson
provided him will come through
but you know it was really about the process That was our main,
that's really what we talked about at CIP
almost exclusively. We also discussed the
town hall
project and the mission creep that's going on there.
And we didn't make, I don't think any decisions about it. We were informed about the situation.
I think that's about all we did, Kurt. You think of anything else?
No, sir.
>> We've
talked about the senior community center building project that we're going to contract for the site engineering preliminary architectural drawings.
So that is on its way that's kind of where we're set up that.
Next meeting what's going to happen with the senior set of community is we're going to start identifying
the services we want to provide the needs we have for
those services to be able to help with the architectural drawings.
And we are going to do site visits for local senior centers to see what
works, what doesn't work, what other towns did, and things like that as a group, and bring that. So that's kind of where we're sitting on that.
Sounds good.
>> Anything
else anybody wants to talk about?
It was a crappy summer with the weather.
It's on record
and it's still raining.
It was wet. That's for sure. Oh, tell you. Mosquitoes will carry you away now.
Good morning. On
the other day out of court. On fire.
>> Yeah.
So can we send some of the rain to California?
I know. Just
>> had relatives who were evacuated.
I think they got back into their house but they live by they have a house at Tahoe and
their house was in the danger zone. They had to evacuate for a week or two.
So yeah, I think all things considered, I like living in a place where it rains.
>> Yeah, I was
there. I was evacuated.
Oh God.
Visiting my son and his family.
>> Were you in the Tahoe area or another? South Lake Tahoe.
Yep. Oh, that's scary. Yeah.
>> Between that and the other what ten years ago when they had a grizzly bear knocked on their door and tear apart all their stuff while they were away,
you know, pass. I'm good with Connecticut, thanks.
>> Do
we have anybody that for public speak? I don't see anybody. Is everything good there?
>> We're good with that. I think we're down to who you see. As
>> always, I want to thank everybody
for all your participation.
I think we all bring good things to the table and everybody has good opinions.
Keep them coming.
Can I have a motion to adjourn?
Motion.
Second.
Second. All in favor?
Aye.
Thank you everybody.
Good evening. Thanks for stepping in as usual.